Preliminary Guide to the Washington Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition records, 1997-2007 MS2168
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Washington Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition records, [olympic bid]
1997-2007
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Knise, Dan
MS2168
14 Linear Feet
These are the records of the Washington, DC 2012 Coalition during its bid for the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games to be held in the Washington Metropolitan Area. The collection includes materials use in the preparation of the Coalition's bid, its final printed preliminary and revised bids, and the International Olympic Committee's reports. The collection also includes materials from other cities' Olympic bids and the 1996 Atlanta, 2000 Sydney and 2004 Athens Olympic and Paralympic Games, which were used to prepare the Coalition's bid.
Tube 22
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dan Knise, 2002
Historical or Biographical Note
The Washington, DC 2012 Coalition was established to bid on the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games. The Coalition consisted of representatives from the District of Columbia, Maryland and Northern Virginia who lobbied the United States Olympic Committee (USOC) to select the D.C. Metropolitan Area as the U.S. candidate city.
Originally entitled the Washington/Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition, the organization was established in 1998 and Dan Knise was named President and Chief Executive Officer. In 2000, it was renamed the Chesapeake Region 2012 Coalition, and finally the Washington, DC 2012 Coalition in May 2001.
The Coalition submitted its initial U.S. bid to the USOC on December 15, 2000. After visiting the bid sites, the USOC selected New York City, the District of Columbia, San Francisco and Houston as U.S. semi-finalists in October 2001. However, New York City and San Francisco were chosen as U.S. finalists in August 2002, and in November, the USOC selected New York City as the U.S. candidate city to be submitted to the International Olympic Committee. On July 6, 2005, London was announced as the site selected for the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains reports, meeting agendas, legislative bills, legal documents, programs, brochures, posters, maps, photographs, video and audio tapes. The material dates in range from 1997-2007. These are the records of the Washington, DC 2012 Coalition during its bid for the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games to be held in the Washington Metropolitan Area. The collection includes materials use in the preparation of the Coalition's bid, its final printed preliminary and revised bids, and the International Olympic Committee's reports. The collection also includes materials from other cities' Olympic bids and the 1996 Atlanta, 2000 Sydney and 2004 Athens Olympic and Paralympic Games, which were used to prepare the Coalition's bid.
Gift of Dan Knise, 2002.
Collection Organization
This collection is not fully processed and does not yet have series designations.
Olympic Games (30th: 2012) -- Proposals; Events; Videotapes; Audiotapes; Baltimore (Md.); Olympic Games; Photographs; Washington (D.C.); Maps
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume I, Themes 1-7 [1/2], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume I, Themes 1-7 [2/2], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume II, Themes 8-10 [1/3], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume II, Themes 8-10 [2/3], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume II, Themes 8-10 [3/3], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume III, Themes 11-18 [1/3], 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume III, Themes 11-18 [2/3], 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- North Carolina Bid Committee, U.S. Candidate City Bid: Volume III, Themes 11-18 [3/3], 2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Action Plan for Green Olympics--Beijing 2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ministry of Culture--Greece, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Tasks and Objectives in view of 2004--Greece Ministry of Culture (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Beijing 2008 brochures (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Athens 2004 brochures (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Toronto 2008 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New York City 2012 bid, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Bill concerning finances for Florida's 2012 bid, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York City 2012 bid information [1/3] (Box 2, Folder 11)
- New York City 2012 bid information [2/3] (Box 2, Folder 12)
- New York City 2012 bid information [3/3] (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Richmond U.S. Olympic Festival Bid (1997, 1998, 1999), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Atlanta 1996 bid information, 1987-1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Athens 2004 Candidate Bid: Volume I (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Athens 2004 Candidate Bid: Volume II [1/2] (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Athens 2004 Candidate Bid: Volume II [2/2] (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Sports Fiesta San Antonio--bid for 2007 Pan American Games: Volume II1, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Sports Fiesta San Antonio--bid for 2007 Pan American Games: Volume III [1/2], 1998 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Sports Fiesta San Antonio--bid for 2007 Pan American Games: Volume III [2/2], 1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Volume I, Themes 1-7, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Volume II, Themes 8-10 [1/2], 2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Volume II, Themes 8-10 [2/2], 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Volume III, Themes 9-11 [1/2], 2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Volume III, Themes 9-11 [2/2], 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Addendum [1/2], 2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Washington D.C. bid proposal for 2012 Olympic Games: Addendum [2/2], 2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Sport Technical Specifications Questionnaire--Washington D.C. 2012 bid (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Paralympic Games Venue and Village Plan Detail--Washington D.C. 2012 bid (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Washington D.C. proposal to host the 2001 VISA American Cup--Gymnastics, 04/2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Washington D.C. proposal to host the 2004 U.S. Olympic Team Trials for Swimming, 04/2001 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Washington D.C. proposal to host the 2004 U.S. Olympic Team Trials--Gymnastics, 04/2001 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Washington Baltimore 2012 Regional Coalition-1999 National Coaching Recognition Program (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Washington D.C. Bid Task Force Meeting--Theme 14 Transportation, 01/07/2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Washington D.C. proposal to host the 2004 USA Marathon Championships, 10/2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- United States Olympic Committee Bid Procedures [1/2], 11/05/1997-11/06/1997 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- United States Olympic Committee Bid Procedures [2/2], 11/05/1997-11/06/1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- United States Olympic Committee Bid Procedures--Sport Technical Specification Manual, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- USOC Site Evaluation Visit--Washington D.C. 2012 [1/2], 06/28/2001-06/29/2001 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- USOC Site Evaluation Visit--Washington D.C. 2012 [2/2], 06/28/2001-06/29/2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Bid City Phase II Guidelines [1/2], 12/07/2001 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Bid City Phase II Guidelines [2/2], 12/07/2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Bid Addendum Task Force--Executive Committee Meeting, 01/07/2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- IOC Rules (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Maryland bid for 1999 Special Olympics World Summer Games, 06/29/1994 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Turkish Olympic Act--Istanbul, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Sydney 2000 Olympic Information: Volume I (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Sydney 2000 Olympic Information: Volume II [1/2] (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Sydney 2000 Olympic Information: Volume II [2/2] (Box 8, Folder 1)
- State of Play: A report to the people of new south wales, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Sydney Media Centre, Darling Island (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Staging the Olympics: The Event and its Impact (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Sydney Airport--Plan for Olympic and Paralympic Visitors, 01/1999 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Olympic City--Central Sydney Roads and Transport for the 2000 Games, 07/1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Beyond 2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Chesapeake Regional Olympic Games Authority Act, 01/08/2001 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Options for Provision of Financial Guarantees, 09/07/2000 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Comparison of Olympic Funding Guarantees, 01/22/2001 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Phase II Guidelines, 12/18/2001 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- The Master Architect Series II: RTKL, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- IOC Olympic Village Guidelines, 01/1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- USOC Bid Procedures (Box 9, Folder 2)
- United States Olympic Committee Bid Procedures--Pan American Games, 11/03/1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Report of the Site Evaluation Task Force for the 2007 Pan American Games, 10/23/1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- IOC/IPC Agreement (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Paralympic Games Bid Information Manual, 05/11/1998-05/13/1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Host City Contract for the Games of the XXVII Olympiad in the Year 2004 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Report of the IOC Evaluation Commission for the Games of the XXIX Olympiad in the Year 2008, 04/03/2001 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Games of the XXIX Olympiad in 2008--Candidate Acceptance Procedure [1/2], 08/18/2000 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Games of the XXIX Olympiad in 2008--Candidate Acceptance Procedure [2/2] (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Candidate Acceptance Procedure--XXI Olympic Winter Games 2010, 12/12/2001 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Agreement for Organizing Committee for the Olympic Games, 01/28/1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Metropolitan Atlanta Olympic Games Authority--Creation, 01/27/1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Atlanta Olympic Games--Finances, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- 1996 Atlanta Games (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Calendar of the Games, 05/1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- The Olympic Legacy: Building on What was Achieved (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Background materials on Atlanta's Olympic bid and organizing, 04/19/1998 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Atlanta General Information Spring, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Financial Aspects of Olympic Contracts, 06/19/1995 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Olympic Contractual Obligations between the Board of Regents of the University System of Georgia and the Atlanta Committee for the Olympic Games, Inc. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Atlanta Olympic Related Federal Funding Projects [1/2] (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Atlanta Olympic Related Federal Funding Projects [2/2] (Box 11, Folder 1)
- The Official Report of the Centennial Olympic Games: Volume I, Planning and Organizing, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- The Official Report of the Centennial Olympic Games: Volume II, The Centennial Olympic Games, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- The Official Report of the Centennial Olympic Games: Volume III, The Competition Results, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Design and Planning for Sydney 2000--Bligh Voller Nield Architects (Box 12, Folder 2)
- USOC Games of the XXVIIth Olympiad Team Leadership Manual, 11/01/1999 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Results of the Games of the XXVII Olympiad (Box 12, Folder 4)
- VIK Planning and Utilization: An Overview (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Inside the U.S. Olympic Movement A to Z (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Olympic Games: Federal Government Provides Significant Funding and Support, 09/2000 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- United States Olympic Committee Directories, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Athens to Atlanta: 100 Years of Glory (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Olympic Medals: A Reference Guide, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Economic Impact of Olympics, 10/12/1998-01/2001 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- IOC/IPC Agreement (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Committee on Commerce Action, 10/14/1999 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Members of AAC, 12/19/2001 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Preliminary Report: The Economic and Fiscal Impacts of the 2012 Olympics, 06/2000 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Constitution, Bylaws and the Ted Stevens Olympic and Amateur Sports Act, 04/15/2000 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Lord Killanin's Speeches, 1972-1981 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Development and Implementation of Facilities, Properties and Projects for Communities, Development Entities, Leagues, Franchises and other Businesses (Box 14, Folder 3)
- U.S. Sports Federations (Box 14, Folder 4)
- H. Res. 601--Expressing the sense of the House of Representatives that without improvement in human rights the Olympic Games in the year 2008 should not be held in Beijing in the People's Republic of China, 09/28/2000 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Agenda 21: Du Mouvrment Olympique (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Legislative materials--Washington DC 2012 Olympic Bid, 11/19/1999 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- The Economic and Fiscal Impacts of Hosting the 2012 Olympic Games in the Washington-Baltimore Metropolitan Area, 12/2000 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Washington-Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition Preliminary Facilities Plan, Venue Selections, 04/14/2000 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Washington/Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition (Box 14, Folder 10)
- 2001 Olympic Winter Games: Estimated Local Government Olympic Revenues, 11/1998 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Materials Relating to Federal Actions in Support of Olympic Bids, Winter 2001 Olympics, 07/1999 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- The Economic Impact on the State of Georgia of Hosting the 1996 Olympic Games [1/2], 06/1995 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- The Economic Impact on the State of Georgia of Hosting the 1996 Olympic Games [2/2], 06/1995 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Research and Information Paper--The Economic Impact of the Sydney Olympic Games, 11/1997 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Investment 2000: Assessing the Legacy (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Sydney 2000, General Information: Volume I (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Sydney 2000, Olympic Information: Volume II [1/2] (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Sydney 2000, Olympic Information: Volume II [2/2] (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Sydney 2000, Technical Information: Volume III (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Washington D.C. 2012, Sample Packet Sent in Response to Volunteer Inquiry, 09/24/2001 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Olympia: Around the Rings (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Sydney 2000 guide books (Box 16, Folder 7)
- CD: Sydney 2000, The Environmental Games (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Sydney 2000, Press Guide (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Information Guide: A summary of Sydney's plans for the 2000 Olympic Games, 01/2000 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Olympic Routes: Road Routes for the Sydney 2000 Olympic Games, 06/1999 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Media Guide: A summery of Sydney's plans for the 2000 Olympic Games, 11/1999 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Sydney 2000, Press Guide, 06/1999 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Design and Planning for Sydney 2000--Bligh Voller Nield Architects (Box 17, Folder 5)
- USOC Coaching Recognition, 09/1999 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Atlanta General Information, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- The Atlanta Financial Context (Box 17, Folder 8)
- U.S. Olympic Congress: 1999 Program, 10/24/1999-10/26/1999 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Marketing Program and Graphic Standards Manual [1/2], 1998 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Marketing Program and Graphic Standards Manual [2/2] (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Official Report of the XXCII Olympiad, Sydney 2000: Volume I, Part 2 [1/3] (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Official Report of the XXCII Olympiad, Sydney 2000: Volume I, Part 2 [2/3] (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Official Report of the XXCII Olympiad, Sydney 2000: Volume I, Part 2 [3/3] (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Olympic Arts Festival, Cultural Olympiad Salt Lake, 2001 (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Video: Washington/Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition Press Conference, 11/06/1998 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Video: Washington/Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition Press Conference, 11/06/1998 (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Video: Gymnastics 2012 PSA Dominique Dawes (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Video: Washington DC 2012 "Youth Sports Days" (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Video: Woman's Soccer 2012 Coalition (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Video: 2012 "Share the Olympic Dream" (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Video: Olympic Coaches Video, 09/16/1999 (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Jim McKay 2012, 09/08/2000 (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Jim McKay 2012, 09/08/2000 (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Video: Washington/Baltimore Regional 2012 Coalition Jim McKay Rough Cut, 08/09/2000 (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Video: WBRC 2012 Jim McKay, Pam Shriver, 09/18/2000 (Box 19, Folder 11)
- Video: WBRC 2012 Jim McKay, 08/28/2000 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Video: D.C. Sports and Entertainment Commission Presents RFK Stadium and The D.C. Armory (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Video: United States Olympic Committee, 1997 U.S. Bid City Seminars Field Tape #7, 11/06/1997 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Video: United States Olympic Committee, 1997 U.S. Bid City Seminars Field Tape #6, 11/06/1997 (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Video: United States Olympic Committee, 1997 U.S. Bid City Seminars Field Tape #5, 11/06/1997 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Audio tape: Wash-Balt 2012, Jam'n 99.5 FM (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Audio tape: Wash-Balt 2012, Jam'n 99.5 FM (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Audio tape: Wash-Balt 2012 Coal. Whitewater, Sports Talk 980 (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Audio tape: Pennsylvania Ave. Mile Spot, Oldies 100 FM WBIG (Box 20, Folder 9)
- Audio tape: DC101 Wash/Balt 2012 (Box 20, Folder 10)
- Downtown Washington, DC Olympic Ceremonial Spaces (Box 21, Item 1)
- Olympic Sports Complex Proposed Legacy Plan (Box 21, Item 2)
- Welcome to the Olympic Sports Complex (Box 21, Item 3)
- Olympic Sports Complex Proposed Olympic Spirit Plaza (Box 21, Item 4)
- Anacostia Waterfront Initiative River front Park System (Box 21, Item 5)
- Organizing Committee of the Olympic Games 2012 Games Budget (Box 21, Item 6)
- Regional Map Proposed Olympic Venues (Box 21A, Item 7)
- Maps of Sydney Olympic Park (Box 20)